How to use ResponseListener

A plugin which implements Swift_Events_ResponseListener will be invoked every time Swift receives a new response from the connection. This can come in useful if used in combination with a CommandListener because if you know what response codes to expect, you can “correct” problems by issuing the RSET command or whatever other action may be appropriate. It probably helps to know a little about the SMTP protocol before attempting such things however.

The plugin receives an instance of Swift_Events_ResponseEvent, which incidentally is the object which gets returned from command() inside Swift. Therefore it would also be technically possible to “trick” Swift into believing that a different response was issued to what was actually issued. Would that be useful? To be honest, I don't know, I've never had cause to do it ;)

Here's the interface:

/**
 * Contains the list of methods a plugin requiring the use of a ResponseEvent must implement
 * @package Swift_Events
 * @author Chris Corbyn <chris@w3style.co.uk>
 */
interface Swift_Events_ResponseListener extends Swift_Events_Listener
{
	/**
	 * Executes when Swift receives a response
	 * @param Swift_Events_ResponseEvent Information about the response
	 */
	public function responseReceived(Swift_Events_ResponseEvent $e);
}

And here's an example of how you might kid Swift that it always receives the response codes it expects. Note that we need to implement two interfaces here.

class NeverArguesBackPlugin
    implements Swift_Events_BeforeCommandListener, Swift_Events_ResponseListener
{
    protected $code;
 
    public function beforeCommandSent(Swift_Events_CommandEvent $e)
    {
        $this->code = $e->getCode();
    }
 
    public function responseReceived(Swift_Events_ResponseEvent $e)
    {
        if ($this->code)
        {
            $e->setCode($this->code);
        }
    }
}

Nasty indeed! :)

Table of Contents

How to (legitimately) minimize being seen as spam

Get a test server if you can

Be compliant with the RFCs

Send from an email address which actually exists!

If you can do so, set up a SPF record (DNS setting)

Don't just send HTML emails!

Don't just send a big image

Don't send really short messages

Are you blacklisted?

And the obvious one....

How to (legitimately) minimize being seen as spam

This is a BIG topic and seemingly one that many people are quite patchy on. I’ll try to give you enough knowledge to make your own judgements and what you could do to minimize your risk. You may finish up sad and disappointed by the end of this article though so don’t build your hopes up that there’s a quick-fix solution if you are being blocked as spam.

Get a test server if you can

If you can do so, I would strongly recommend setting up a test server running SA-Exim. That’s Exim with SpamAssassin. This will allow you to mock out the process of sending your newsletter or whatever else you’re sending. You can configure Exim to append a spam report on what it finds into your headers. Most Linux distros will have some pre-packaged version for you. If yours doesn’t (ArchLinux doesn’t as far as I know) then you’ll have to roll your own. How to do that is outside of the scope of this article unfortunately but essentially you need to install both Exim4 and SpamAssassin on the same server, then edit your exim.conf file to run a new router which looks for spam.

Using a pre-packaged versions can be as easy as:

On Debian systems:

apt-get update
apt-get install sa-exim

Check your own distro’s user forums if you’re unsure.

Once you have those installed, you simply need to create a user account on the server, set it as a MX record for one of your domains and then send emails to $user@$domain. When you view the source code of the emails you’ll see a section relating to spam filtering with some scores in it. Usually it will tell you what the threshold is for being blocked as spam - 5 by default! 5.0 is a leniant score too... If you go over 2.5 I’d say something’s not right.

Look at the breakdown of where your points came from... usually they’re quite self explanatory such as EMAIL_SUBJECT_TWICE or something like that.

Be compliant with the RFCs

The RFCs main involved here are RFC2822 and RFC2045. You’re lucky someone else already did all the hard work for you :) That’s what Swift is made for. Endless hours of reading RFCs, sending to many different SMTP servers running different software and checking results.

The RFCs cover things such as maximum line length (1000, but 78 is a safer option), the structure of headers, character sets which are valid etc. If you were just using mail() you’d have a lot to think about but Swift does lots of things under-the-hood in terms of encoding, line shortening, building compliant headers, putting MIME sections in the correct places, identifying langauges and other important points.

Spam checkers almost all look for incompliant emails.

Basically, don’t worry about this if you’re using Swift, just remember that it’s a factor in spam checking.

Send from an email address which actually exists!

This is REALLY important. The most important thing is that the domain has a MX record which can be publically looked up. The local part of the address is less important although I’d still recommend sending from a working email account.

Check your MX records are working by using a tool such as DIG if you have access to a Linux server or a UNIX/OS X system. You can probably get DIG for windows too.

The command to run is

dig MX <domain-name.tld>

You need an MX record for each subdomain too. If you have joe@yourdomain.tld you need a MX record for yourdomain.tld, then if you have joe@users.yourdomain.tld you need a separate MX record for users.yourdomain.tld.

Here’s an example output if the MX record is working:

w3style:~ d11wtq$ dig MX gmail.com

; <<>> DiG 9.3.2 <<>> MX gmail.com
;; global options:  printcmd
;; Got answer:
;; ->>HEADER<<- opcode: QUERY, status: NOERROR, id: 8709
;; flags: qr rd ra; QUERY: 1, ANSWER: 5, AUTHORITY: 0, ADDITIONAL: 0

;; QUESTION SECTION:
;gmail.com.                     IN      MX

;; ANSWER SECTION:
gmail.com.              1192    IN      MX      10 alt1.gmail-smtp-in.l.google.com.
gmail.com.              1192    IN      MX      10 alt2.gmail-smtp-in.l.google.com.
gmail.com.              1192    IN      MX      50 gsmtp163.google.com.
gmail.com.              1192    IN      MX      50 gsmtp183.google.com.
gmail.com.              1192    IN      MX      5 gmail-smtp-in.l.google.com.

;; Query time: 18 msec
;; SERVER: 194.168.4.100#53(194.168.4.100)
;; WHEN: Thu Feb 15 10:07:03 2007
;; MSG SIZE  rcvd: 158

w3style:~ d11wtq$

And here’s the output if it’s not working

w3style:~ d11wtq$ dig MX calendar.w3style.org

; <<>> DiG 9.3.2 <<>> MX calendar.w3style.org
;; global options:  printcmd
;; Got answer:
;; ->>HEADER<<- opcode: QUERY, status: NOERROR, id: 31483
;; flags: qr rd ra; QUERY: 1, ANSWER: 0, AUTHORITY: 1, ADDITIONAL: 0

;; QUESTION SECTION:
;calendar.w3style.org.          IN      MX

;; AUTHORITY SECTION:
w3style.org.            3600    IN      SOA     ns1.w3style.co.uk. admin.w3style.co.uk. 2007020801 28800 7200 604800 86400

;; Query time: 22 msec
;; SERVER: 194.168.4.100#53(194.168.4.100)
;; WHEN: Thu Feb 15 10:10:46 2007
;; MSG SIZE  rcvd: 97

w3style:~ d11wtq$

If you don’t have a MX record for the email address you’re using then the email won’t function in any case which suggests you never intended to use the mailbox. If you decide to set up a MX record, remember that changes could take 24 hours or so to propogate around all the nameservers in the world. Usually it’s only a matter of a few hours these days though. If you tried looking up your MX record immediately after you set it up and it wasn’t found, you may be stuck for a while being provided with cached results from your DNS servers. Just be patient and wait :)

If you can do so, set up a SPF record (DNS setting)

Some of the major email providers such as Hotmail actually penalize you to the point you stand very little chance of successfully delivering mail if you do not have a SPF record set up for the domain your are sending email from. You can find out more about SPF at the official website: http://www.openspf.org/

What SPF basically does is limits the number of locations people can send email from your address from.

It’s not as scary as it looks. DNS records have differing types such as A, CNAME, MX, SOA, PTR and TXT. It’s a TXT record you need to set up. The page linked to above explains how to do this better than I can - I admit that you may have to read it several times before it sinks in!

If you’re sending email from joe@yourdomain.tld then the TXT record needs to be set on yourdomain.tld, and if you send from joe@users.yourdomain.tld the TXT record needs to be set for users.yourdomain.tld.

Remember that because this is a DNS setting you may have to wait up to 24 hours for your changes to have any effect.

Don't just send HTML emails!

If you’re going to send a HTML email, great! But always duplicate the same email in plain text and send the message as a multipart message. Spam checkers, belive it or not, do penalize you for sending HTML-only emails. Sending a multipart email not only lowers your spam score, it also increases the number of people who will be able to actually read the email since not all mail clients can read HTML.

Don't just send a big image

For aesthetic reasons, people sometimes will just send a big graphic done in Illustrator or similar software. This is a definite no-no. Some email clients won’t display the image and more importantly it gets you almost definitely caught in a spam filter!

Don't send really short messages

I know it’s stupid, but it does make a difference. A short email (as in one sentence) is more likely be tagged as spam than a long one.

Are you blacklisted?

It may surprise you, but there’s a chance - through no immediate fault of your own - that you may be on a blacklist. Spam checkers can use a system called RBL (Real Time Blacklists). These are huge online databases which keep track of suspected/known spammers. They tag the IP address of the originating server and occassionally will tag an entire submask. Shared servers often inevitably finish up on these lists because they become a high target for spammers who roam from one shared account to another. Bottom line - don’t rely on shared hosting to deliver emails.

You can check if any of your IP addresses (hosting, and SMTP server) are in a blacklist by going here:

http://www.robtex.com/rbls.html

If you’re unfortunate enough to find that you’re on a blacklist there’s sadly not a lot you can do apart from changing your IP address.

I mentioned SPF records above... if you don’t have an SPF record, your chance of appearing on a blacklist is increased since bots will try to use your email address as a MAIL FROM envelope (so they don’t get a load of boucned email messages - you do!). If you have your SMTP server set up as an open relay, well, you’re just asking for it really :P

NOTE: If you’re trying to run a SMTP server on a dynamic IP - even with a domain name from dyndns or similar - you will almost definitly appear on the blacklists. Dynamic IP addresses are usually blacklisted by default. Get a static IP.

And the obvious one....

The obvious thing that WILL get you stuck in a spam filter is sending junk. People can pretty-up the term any way they like and call it a marketing campaign or whatever but i you’re sending emails advertising something to people who didn’t give you their email address you are spamming.

Emails containing talk of millions or thousands of dollars/pounds, cracked software, pornographic text, drugs and any other obvious spam-type topics are just going to be tagged as spam. Don’t do it.

Table of Contents

Dealing with Attachments

Attaching the file contents as a string read externally

Attaching the file contents using the Swift_File class

So which method do you use?

What's the content disposition for?

Dealing with Attachments

Synopsis: new Swift_Message_Attachment([mixed data [, string filename [, string content-type [, string encoding [, string disposition]]]]])

An attachment yet again, another MIME document. It’s special because it contains any format of data such as a PDF, a Zip file or an executable. In order for SMTP to proccess such data it gets encoded into a format which looks like plain-text (such as Base64).

When you create an attachment, you have two means of providing the contents of the file; You can read them yourself using something like file_get_contents(), or you can pass a file object to the attachment to allow it to read the file itself. We’ll look at both approaches here and assess where either one is more suitable than the other.

Attaching the file contents as a string read externally

$message =& new Swift_Message("My subject");
 
$file_data = file_get_contents("foo.pdf");
$attachment =& new Swift_Message_Attachment($file_data, "foo.pdf");
 
$message->attach($attachment);

When we attach the file as a string, the Attachment class does not know its filename so we need to re-confirm it by passing it as a parameter. If we didn’t do this, the Attachment class would give it a name like “file.1” which makes no sense to the recipient.

I hesitate to go into the inner workings of the Attachment class here, but for the sake of clarification I’ll touch on how the encoding works. When you provide a string in this way, the attachment class takes the entire string and base64 encodes that data at the time the message is rendered. You’ll see why I’ve mentioned that after we look at the next approach to providing an attachment.

Attaching the file contents using the Swift_File class

$message =& new Swift_Message("My subject");
 
$file =& new Swift_File("foo.pdf");
$attachment =& new Swift_Message_Attachment($file);
 
$message->attach($attachment);

Not much different then? Well no, not really. But it does have its advantages in certain scenarios.

Swift_File does not read the entire file contents in one go, it reads the file in small chunks of bytes and therefore allows encoding in smaller portions. This has two advantages when encoding:

It speeds up the encoding process (I’ve still not understood exactly “why”, but my testing shows it does)

It saves a considerable amount memory

PHP imposes a 8 megabyte memory limit on scripts by default (I believe this has been raised to 16MB in PHP 5.2.0). This can very easily be exhausted when you use the first method of adding an attachment if you’re attaching a file with a size of say, 2MB. This is because you have a copy of the 2MB in memory, you then have a base64 encoded copy in memory which is 33% larger than the original (2.66MB) plus the overhead of the encoding process and a copy which is cached to reduce CPU cycles. This soon uses a lot of memory.

So which method do you use?

By using Swift_File you save memory by not having the file contents in memory, and by not having such a large overhead in encoding. This is the preferred method for attaching large files.

Additionally, using Swift_File allows you to leave out the filename parameter in Swift_Message_Attachment since it provides the filename itself.

So why provide the string method at all?

Simple. Imagine you create an image with GD or a PDF with the R&OS PDF library. Do you want to have to write the file to the server only to read it and delete it again? The string method of attaching files is designed to allow dynmically generated content to be attached.

NOTE: The content-type defaults to application/octet-stream. You’ll probably want to specify the correct content-type yourself. In the above example this would be “application/pdf”.

[TODO: List MIME types in the documentation]

TIP: It’s a little known secret that passing an instance of Swift_File to provide the data for the attachment is actually handled by the MIME layer itself. Swift_Message, Swift_Message_Part and all the other MIME features extend this layer and thus, you can pass an instance of Swift_File to Swift_Message to create the message body from a text or HTML file. Equally you can pass a file object to Swift_Message_Part to provide the message body.

What's the content disposition for?

Attachments are by default nested into an email with a tag to indicate they are “attachment” data. This tag is known as its disposition. You can alternatively attach a file as “inline” such as the case where you add an embedded image. It’s unlikely you’ll ever need to specify the disposition manually, but the feature exists anyway. Note that you can use setDisposition() if you’d rather not use the constructor.

Keep memory down to a minimum

If you're sending out a large batch of emails (in the thousands of recipients) you probably need to think slightly more about your approach to delivering the emails. In general, if you can send two emails in a loop using X amount of memory, you should only need a negligible amount more memory to send out ten thousand. Obviously you need more time too!

Your typical default installation of PHP will have a memory limit of 8MB in the configuration. This is more than enough for the average web page request. However, when you start performing intensive tasks such as sending out HUGE amounts of emails you need to be aware of where you can shave off some memory. Before going any further, if you need to send attachments larger than 2.5MB you should increase PHP's memory limit.

I can quite clearly tell you where PHP uses memory, it's clear-cut, and using a tool like XDebug will clarify this.

Encoding data

Storing all variable data in original form

Caching “rendered” data

Logging network communication data

You can shave a considerable amount of memory from your scripts by:

Don't enable logging, or write a custom file/DB logger

Encoding file data via a “streamed” mechanism by using a Swift_File object rather than a raw string

Unlike version 2 of Swift Mailer, no logging is done unless you request it. To request logging, use:

$swift->log->enable();

By default, 50 log items will be stored. This includes each SMTP line sent - which incidentally includes the message body. It's advised to set the log size to a maximum length of 1, or disable it completely if you need to send a large batch.

To do that:

$swift->log->setMaxSize(1);

If you're sending attachments, it's advised that you don't read the file contents as a string and that you use the Swift_File class instead. Using Swift_File streams data rather than copying it into memory.

$attachment =& new Swift_Mesage_Attachment(new Swift_File("foo.zip"));

Spread the load

If you use the Sendmail or NativeMail classes to connect, you have to remember where the email sending is being processed. Swift issues the commands, and the same server does the sending. Therefore you put a fairly high demand on the one server. By using the SMTP connection class you spread the load over two servers because Swift tells the SMTP server what to do. Even better still, take advantage of the Rotator connection which will spread the load over as many servers as you can get your hands on.

NOTE: I wouldn't recommend using the rotator connection unless you're going to send a relatively large batch; You have to take into account the small amount of overhead involved in establishing the initial connection with each server.

Use Disk Caching

If you're sending attachments, this is definitely something you should do if you can. Swift already uses caching under-the-hood. By default it will cache to memory at runtime which of course, uses memory. If you have an 8MB memory limit on your PHP install, you'll not likely send any attachments of more than about 3MB with this setup. Luckily, Swift's caching system is abstract and there's a Disk Caching mechanism provided. All you need to a writable directory somewhere on disk. ”/tmp” will usually be fine to use. Swift will then create temporary files at runtime and delete them once it's finished. This drastically lowers memory. If you're sending attachments, you can send any size you like (say 100MB?) by using Swift_File when you add the attachment and Disk Caching. Here's how you enable disk caching.

$swift =& new Swift( ... );
 
//You change the cache class using this call...
Swift_CacheFactory::setClassName("Swift_Disk_Cache");
 
//Then you set up the disk cache to write to a writable folder...
Swift_Disk_Cache::setSavePath("/home/username/tmp");
 
//then work as normal...

It may be tempting to think that caching to disk is slow. It probably is when you compare the relative speeds with using memory, but think about it… Swift uses network connections… is the Disk Cache going to have an impact over the top of a network connection overhead? No ;)

NOTE: This has been proven to send a 100MB attachment and use just 1MB of memory on a PHP4 installation of Swift. Use it if you can.